<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Anthony Faustine&#39;s blog</title>
<link>https://sambaiga.github.io/atom.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://sambaiga.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Anthony Faustine&#39;s blog</description>
<language>en</language>
<generator>quarto-1.8.26</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 23:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Capabilities vs. Routines: Operationalizing Dynamic Strategy with Corporate Foresight (Part 2/3)</title>
  <dc:creator>Anthony Faustine</dc:creator>
  <link>https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/09/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="introduction" class="level1">
<h1>Introduction</h1>
<p>In Part 1, we established that <strong>Dynamic Capabilities</strong> are the essential strategic ability for firms to continuously reconfigure their resources to achieve competitive advantage. Here, we dive into the theoretical and practical framework that explains <em>how</em> this continuous adaptation actually happens.</p>
</section>
<section id="two-streams-of-research-capabilities-vs.-routines" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Two Streams of Research: Capabilities vs.&nbsp;Routines</h1>
<p>While the core definition of dynamic capabilities remains consistent, academic literature divides the concept into two complementary streams that focus on different aspects: <strong>Capabilities</strong> (the managerial view) and <strong>Routines</strong> (the process view).</p>
<section id="the-capabilities-view-teece-1997" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-capabilities-view-teece-1997">The Capabilities View (Teece, 1997)</h2>
<p>This influential stream, built on the work of <span class="citation" data-cites="teece1997dynamic">(<strong>teece1997dynamic?</strong>)</span>, views dynamic capabilities as <strong>organizational capabilities</strong> that are flexible, adaptable, and distinct from everyday routines. The emphasis is on management’s role in <strong>reconfiguring resources and assets</strong> to address market changes <span class="citation" data-cites="teece2012dynamic teece2014dynamic">(<strong>teece2012dynamic?</strong>; <strong>teece2014dynamic?</strong>)</span>.</p>
<p>According to this perspective, dynamic capabilities are the key competence for sustained growth, enabling firms to align and re-align resources quickly to generate abnormal returns <span class="citation" data-cites="teece2012dynamic">(<strong>teece2012dynamic?</strong>)</span>. The critical ingredients are <strong>management capabilities</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Managerial &amp; Entrepreneurial Action:</strong> Good strategies, execution, and difficult-to-imitate combinations of organizational, functional, and technological skills <span class="citation" data-cites="teece1997dynamic schwarz2rohrbecf">(<strong>teece1997dynamic?</strong>; <strong>schwarz2rohrbecf?</strong>)</span>.</li>
<li><strong>Organizational Pillars:</strong> The firm’s capability rests on the <em>vision and leadership skills of managers</em> and the <em>cohesion and flexibility of the organization as a whole</em> <span class="citation" data-cites="schwarz2rohrbecf">(<strong>schwarz2rohrbecf?</strong>)</span>.</li>
</ul>
<p>This view also incorporates the six crucial capabilities of entrepreneurial leaders: <strong>anticipate, challenge, interpret, decide, align, and learn</strong> <span class="citation" data-cites="day2016adapting">(<strong>day2016adapting?</strong>)</span>, which must be applied together <span class="citation" data-cites="schwarz2rohrbecf">(<strong>schwarz2rohrbecf?</strong>)</span>.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-routines-view-eisenhardt-martin-2000" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-routines-view-eisenhardt-martin-2000">The Routines View (Eisenhardt &amp; Martin, 2000)</h2>
<p>In contrast, the stream led by <span class="citation" data-cites="eisenhardt2000dynamic">(<strong>eisenhardt2000dynamic?</strong>)</span> focuses on the operational aspect, viewing dynamic capability as <strong>context-specific <em>routines</em> or <em>processes</em></strong> that organizations use to achieve strategic fit with their environment.</p>
<p>These are observable processes that reside in existing functions like product development, strategic decision-making, resource allocation, alliances, and R&amp;D <span class="citation" data-cites="eisenhardt2000dynamic schwarz2rohrbecf">(<strong>eisenhardt2000dynamic?</strong>; <strong>schwarz2rohrbecf?</strong>)</span>. This approach highlights the varied, practical capabilities firms use to adapt and evolve in response to changes, providing concrete examples of how dynamic capabilities are enacted.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="the-combined-framework-and-operationalization" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-combined-framework-and-operationalization">The Combined Framework and Operationalization</h2>
<p>The two streams of dynamic capabilities—Teece’s focus on managerial <strong>Capabilities</strong> and Eisenhardt’s focus on <strong>Routines</strong>—are not opposing theories, but rather <strong>complementary views</strong> of the same strategic ability.</p>
<p>The <span class="citation" data-cites="teece1997dynamic">(<strong>teece1997dynamic?</strong>)</span> and <span class="citation" data-cites="eisenhardt2000dynamic">(<strong>eisenhardt2000dynamic?</strong>)</span> dynamic capabilities views are complementary and can be combined as illustrated in Figure&nbsp;1. It becomes evident that dynamic capabilities, as perceived by <span class="citation" data-cites="teece1997dynamic">(<strong>teece1997dynamic?</strong>)</span>, need established routines and processes for them to contribute to a competitive advantage and attain sustained firm performance. These routines and processes can be seen as the <strong>operationalization of dynamic capabilities</strong>, allowing a firm to effectively align and re-align its resources to meet the demands and opportunities of the business environment. Without these routines and processes in place, the ability to develop and acquire new resources and assets may not be fully realized, and the firm may not be able to achieve sustained performance.</p>
<p>This perspective aligns with the results presented in <span class="citation" data-cites="di2014organizational">(<strong>di2014organizational?</strong>)</span>, which suggests that dynamic capabilities are not only about the development and acquisition of new resources and assets, but also about the ability to put these resources and assets into action through established routines and processes. <span class="citation" data-cites="di2014organizational">(<strong>di2014organizational?</strong>)</span> emphasizes that both <strong>latent capabilities</strong> (<span class="citation" data-cites="teece1997dynamic">(<strong>teece1997dynamic?</strong>)</span> view) and <strong>observable routines</strong> are important for firms to achieve sustainable growth and competitiveness <span class="citation" data-cites="di2014organizational">(<strong>di2014organizational?</strong>)</span>.</p>
<p>Furthermore, <span class="citation" data-cites="kump2019toward">(<strong>kump2019toward?</strong>)</span> argues that firms may possess high levels of certain aspects of dynamic capabilities and have established reliable routines that lead to similar dynamic capabilities outcomes, but they may differ in terms of the concrete methods and structures of how they achieve these dynamic capabilities outcomes. This <strong>diversity in implementation</strong> of dynamic capabilities can also be a source of competitive advantage <span class="citation" data-cites="kump2019toward">(<strong>kump2019toward?</strong>)</span>.</p>
<div id="fig-dc-framework" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored page-columns page-full">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure page-columns page-full">
<div aria-describedby="fig-dc-framework-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca" class="page-columns page-full">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/09/Figures/Framework-of-the-dynamic-capability-theory-23-PSM-capabilities-for-a-more-resilient.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Dynamic capability framework combining capability and routine views <em>source</em>: <span class="citation" data-cites="pereira2015role">(<strong>pereira2015role?</strong>)</span></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-margin quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig quarto-uncaptioned" id="fig-dc-framework-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;1
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="the-role-of-corporate-foresight-cultivating-dynamic-capability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-role-of-corporate-foresight-cultivating-dynamic-capability">The Role of Corporate Foresight: Cultivating Dynamic Capability</h2>
<p>The practical question remains: how are these complex capabilities and routines actually cultivated? A growing body of work points to <strong>Corporate Foresight</strong> as a crucial mechanism.</p>
<p>A recent study by <span class="citation" data-cites="schwarz2rohrbecf">(<strong>schwarz2rohrbecf?</strong>)</span> posits that the incorporation of corporate foresight (CF) practices at the organizational level and individual level is likely to have a beneficial effect on the cultivation and resultant outcome of dynamic capabilities. Corporate foresight has been described as a set of intentional and often routine-based practices that organizations adopt to anticipate and prepare for future change. It can also be seen as an individual ability to envision and plan for the future <span class="citation" data-cites="schwarz2hrbecf">(<strong>schwarz2hrbecf?</strong>)</span>.</p>
<p>This concept neatly maps onto the two main theoretical streams: <span class="citation" data-cites="schwarz2rohrbecf">(<strong>schwarz2rohrbecf?</strong>)</span> conceptualised corporate foresight practices on the organisational level as deliberate practices that an organisation has built and that often are routinised (<em><span class="citation" data-cites="eisenhardt2000dynamic">(<strong>eisenhardt2000dynamic?</strong>)</span> view</em>) and on an individual level as <strong>managerial capabilities</strong> (<em><span class="citation" data-cites="teece1997dynamic">(<strong>teece1997dynamic?</strong>)</span> view</em>) such as managerial cognition, managerial social capital, and managerial human capital <span class="citation" data-cites="schwarz2rohrbecf">(<strong>schwarz2rohrbecf?</strong>)</span>. The study discovered that the implementation of corporate foresight practices and training can aid in the growth of a company’s dynamic capabilities <span class="citation" data-cites="schwarz2rohrbecf">(<strong>schwarz2rohrbecf?</strong>)</span>. This finding aligns with <span class="citation" data-cites="day2016adapting">(<strong>day2016adapting?</strong>)</span>, who argue that corporate foresight training and practices have a significant impact on dynamic managerial capabilities and dynamic capabilities at the organizational level. Furthermore, it emphasizes that dynamic capabilities are not only based on traditional processes like research and development, strategic partnerships, and decision-making, as previously proposed by <span class="citation" data-cites="eisenhardt2000dynamic">(<strong>eisenhardt2000dynamic?</strong>)</span>.</p>
<hr>
</section>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level1">
<h1>Conclusion</h1>
<p>We’ve established that dynamic capabilities require both <strong>managerial vision</strong> and <strong>concrete routines</strong>, which can be fostered through <strong>Corporate Foresight</strong>. But what is the sequential, step-by-step process every firm must follow to make this adaptation happen?</p>
<p>In our final post, we break down the three actionable dimensions of dynamic capabilities: <strong>Sensing, Seizing, and Transforming</strong>.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-faustine2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Faustine, Anthony. 2024. <span>“Capabilities Vs. Routines:
Operationalizing Dynamic Strategy with Corporate Foresight (Part
2/3).”</span> September 1, 2024. <a href="https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/09/">https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/09/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Strategy</category>
  <category>Leadership</category>
  <guid>https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/09/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/09/dynamic-capability.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Dynamic Capabilities: Why Reconfiguring Resources is Your Only Path to Long-Term Success (Part 1/3)</title>
  <dc:creator>Anthony Faustine</dc:creator>
  <link>https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/08/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="introduction" class="level1">
<h1>Introduction</h1>
<p>Competition in high-technology industries worldwide has shown that accumulating valuable technologies, often protected by aggressive intellectual property strategies, is not sufficient for success <span class="citation" data-cites="teece1997dynamic">(Teece, Pisano, and Shuen 1997)</span>. Instead, the most successful firms such as Microsoft, Tesla, Intel to name a few, have developed specific capabilities, including the ability to rapidly and flexibly innovate products and the management skills to coordinate and redeploy market positions and explore new opportunities effectively <span class="citation" data-cites="teece1997dynamic">(Teece, Pisano, and Shuen 1997)</span>.</p>
<p>As stated by <span class="citation" data-cites="witschel2019riding">Witschel et al. (2019)</span>, only companies with unique abilities can adjust their resources to a constantly changing environment and effectively utilise the opportunities that arise from these changes. These capabilities are developed through the organisation’s learning process and cannot be obtained from the external environment <span class="citation" data-cites="witschel2019riding matysiak2018dynamic">(Witschel et al. 2019; Matysiak, Rugman, and Bausch 2018)</span>. The author further stress that difficult-to-replicate capabilities are essential to sustain long-term competitiveness. These capabilities and timely responsiveness are crucial to achieving competitive advantage in these industries and are referred to as <strong>dynamic capabilities</strong>.</p>
</section>
<section id="dynamic-capabilities-the-engine-of-strategic-renewal" class="level1">
<h1>Dynamic Capabilities: The Engine of Strategic Renewal</h1>
<p>The concept of Dynamic Capabilities is central to understanding how firms not just survive, but <strong>thrive</strong>, in volatile, fast-paced markets. Simply possessing valuable resources isn’t enough; success depends on the <strong>ability to change those resources</strong> when the environment demands it.</p>
<p>The foundational definition by <span class="citation" data-cites="teece1997dynamic">Teece, Pisano, and Shuen (1997)</span> establishes dynamic capabilities as the firm’s ability to <strong>integrate, build, and reconfigure internal and external competencies</strong> to address rapidly changing environments. This capability enables a firm to develop and acquire new resources and assets and reconfigure them as needed to innovate and stay competitive <span class="citation" data-cites="teece2014dynamic">(Teece 2014)</span>. Crucially, there is academic agreement that this capability acts as an internal mechanism for deliberately altering a company’s current set of resources and aligning them with new strategic objectives, ultimately resulting in a fresh combination or arrangement of organizational assets <span class="citation" data-cites="Zahra2022 witschel2019riding">(Zahra, Petricevic, and Luo 2022; Witschel et al. 2019)</span>.</p>
<p>Expanding on Teece’s perspective, subsequent definitions emphasize the continuous and global nature of this process. For instance, <span class="citation" data-cites="Zahra2022">Zahra, Petricevic, and Luo (2022)</span> refines the concept as the firm’s ability to effectively and continuously <strong>build, bundle, mobilise, integrate, reconfigure, upgrade and protect critical resources</strong> to address rapidly changing environments in geographically dispersed markets. Similarly, <span class="citation" data-cites="witschel2019riding">Witschel et al. (2019)</span> views dynamic capabilities as reflecting an organisation’s ability to create new and innovative forms of competitive advantage, rooted in its history and market position <span class="citation" data-cites="witschel2019riding">(Witschel et al. 2019)</span>.</p>
<p>These capabilities are also fundamentally tied to problem-solving and environmental awareness. <span class="citation" data-cites="barreto2010dynamic">Barreto (2010)</span> define them as a firm’s potential to <strong>systematically solve problems</strong>, formed by its ability to <strong>sense opportunities and threats</strong>, make timely and market-oriented decisions, and change its resource base <span class="citation" data-cites="barreto2010dynamic schwarz2rohrbecf">(Barreto 2010; Schwarz, Rohrbeck, and Wach 2020)</span>. This highlights the necessity of being proactive, which <span class="citation" data-cites="wilden2013dynamic">Wilden et al. (2013)</span> further specifies: the ability to sense changes requires a firm to closely <strong>observe customers, suppliers, R&amp;D partners, and changes in technology</strong>, suggesting that <strong>anticipatory processes and tools</strong> play an important role in dynamic capabilities <span class="citation" data-cites="schwarz2rohrbecf wilden2013dynamic">(Schwarz, Rohrbeck, and Wach 2020; Wilden et al. 2013)</span>.</p>
<p>In essence, while the specific wording varies, all these definitions converge on dynamic capabilities being the strategic, continuous, and difficult-to-replicate ability of a firm to <strong>adapt its internal structure and resources</strong> in anticipation of or in response to external shifts, securing long-term competitiveness.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level1">
<h1>Conclusion</h1>
<p>The consensus is clear: <strong>Dynamic Capabilities are a strategic necessity</strong>. They represent the essential managerial ability to ensure a firm’s assets remain relevant in a complex, fast-moving world. But how does a firm actually <em>build</em> and <em>execute</em> this continuous transformation?</p>
<p>In the next post, we will explore the two dominant schools of thought that explain the difference between high-level managerial vision and the concrete processes required to turn vision into reality: the <strong>Capabilities vs.&nbsp;Routines</strong> debate.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-barreto2010dynamic" class="csl-entry">
Barreto, Ilı́dio. 2010. <span>“Dynamic Capabilities: A Review of Past Research and an Agenda for the Future.”</span> <em>Journal of Management</em> 36 (1): 256–80.
</div>
<div id="ref-matysiak2018dynamic" class="csl-entry">
Matysiak, Lars, Alan M Rugman, and Andreas Bausch. 2018. <span>“Dynamic Capabilities of Multinational Enterprises: The Dominant Logics Behind Sensing, Seizing, and Transforming Matter!”</span> <em>Management International Review</em> 58 (2): 225–50.
</div>
<div id="ref-schwarz2rohrbecf" class="csl-entry">
Schwarz, Jan Oliver, René Rohrbeck, and Bernhard Wach. 2020. <span>“Corporate Foresight as a Microfoundation of Dynamic Capabilities.”</span> <em>Futures &amp; Foresight Science</em> 2 (2): e28.
</div>
<div id="ref-teece2014dynamic" class="csl-entry">
Teece, David J. 2014. <span>“A Dynamic Capabilities-Based Entrepreneurial Theory of the Multinational Enterprise.”</span> <em>Journal of International Business Studies</em> 45 (1): 8–37.
</div>
<div id="ref-teece1997dynamic" class="csl-entry">
Teece, David J, Gary Pisano, and Amy Shuen. 1997. <span>“Dynamic Capabilities and Strategic Management.”</span> <em>Strategic Management Journal</em> 18 (7): 509–33.
</div>
<div id="ref-wilden2013dynamic" class="csl-entry">
Wilden, Ralf, Siegfried P Gudergan, Bo Bernhard Nielsen, and Ian Lings. 2013. <span>“Dynamic Capabilities and Performance: Strategy, Structure and Environment.”</span> <em>Long Range Planning</em> 46 (1-2): 72–96.
</div>
<div id="ref-witschel2019riding" class="csl-entry">
Witschel, Daliborka, Aaron Döhla, Maximilian Kaiser, Kai-Ingo Voigt, and Thilo Pfletschinger. 2019. <span>“Riding on the Wave of Digitization: Insights How and Under What Settings Dynamic Capabilities Facilitate Digital-Driven Business Model Change.”</span> <em>Journal of Business Economics</em> 89 (8): 1023–95.
</div>
<div id="ref-Zahra2022" class="csl-entry">
Zahra, Shaker A., Olga Petricevic, and Yadong Luo. 2022. <span>“Toward an Action-Based View of Dynamic Capabilities for International Business.”</span> <em>Journal of International Business Studies</em> 53 (4): 583–600. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1057/s41267-021-00487-2">https://doi.org/10.1057/s41267-021-00487-2</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-faustine2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Faustine, Anthony. 2024. <span>“Dynamic Capabilities: Why Reconfiguring
Resources Is Your Only Path to Long-Term Success (Part 1/3).”</span>
August 1, 2024. <a href="https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/08/">https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/08/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Strategy</category>
  <category>Leadership</category>
  <guid>https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/08/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/08/dynamic-capability.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Shared Mental Models: The Invisible Architecture of High-Performance Teams</title>
  <dc:creator>Anthony Faustine</dc:creator>
  <link>https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/07/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="introduction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>Ever been on a team where everything just <em>clicks</em>? communication is effortless, everyone knows their role, and the team anticipates each other’s moves, achieving goals with remarkable efficiency. This seamless collaboration is not a magic. It is often the result of something called a <strong>shared mental model</strong>, the invisible architecture that supports high-performance teamwork.</p>
<p>This post explores what shared mental models are, why they are a critical predictor of team effectiveness, and how leaders can consciously cultivate them, especially in the complex environments of virtual and hybrid teams.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-is-a-shared-mental-model" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-a-shared-mental-model">What is a Shared Mental Model?</h2>
<p>Team effectiveness and coordination are critical aspects of a high-performance team. Team members who share a similar and organized understanding of team tasks and goals — and who understand each other’s working environments — are more likely to perform well.</p>
<p>This shared understanding and knowledge about the mission, goals, and other relevant environments among team members are called <strong>mental models</strong>. The shared mental model is one of the most frequently used concepts in team cognition <span class="citation" data-cites="Schelble2022">(Schelble et al. 2022)</span>. <span class="citation" data-cites="Lungeanu2022">(2022)</span> further identify the shared mental model as a critical predictor of team effectiveness.</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Lungeanu2022">Lungeanu, DeChurch, and Contractor (2022)</span> define shared mental models as team properties reflecting how team members organize knowledge and understanding about the team’s purpose, the nature of the work, and how they work together. Thus, team mental models are a collective mental representation among team members of how they interact in performing task-work <span class="citation" data-cites="Larson2020">(Larson and DeChurch 2020)</span>.</p>
<p>They represent the organized mental representations of the various component pieces relevant to a team’s overall task <span class="citation" data-cites="Schelble2022">(Schelble et al. 2022)</span>. As <span class="citation" data-cites="Schelble2022">(Schelble et al. 2022)</span> point out, shared mental models measure whether or not team members share a common understanding of their shared tasks, roles, interdependencies, and strategies.</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Schelble2022">Schelble et al. (2022)</span> break shared mental models into two types:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Task mental model</strong> — covers aspects specific to understanding and completing a shared task.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Team mental model</strong> — focuses on factors related to cooperation and communication within a team.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="the-impact-on-team-success" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-impact-on-team-success">The Impact on Team Success</h2>
<p>Shared mental models can continually develop over time, becoming more effective and influencing various team outcomes, such as objective performance, team viability, member well-being, and strategic alignment <span class="citation" data-cites="Lungeanu2022">(Lungeanu, DeChurch, and Contractor 2022)</span>.</p>
<p>Teams with shared mental models can recognize one another’s needs and information requirements <span class="citation" data-cites="Lungeanu2022 Schelble2022">(Lungeanu, DeChurch, and Contractor 2022; Schelble et al. 2022)</span>, which enhances coordination and mutual support.</p>
<p>While this may be more intuitive in physical teams, virtual teams — now an integral part of modern work — require special attention in developing and maintaining shared mental models among members.</p>
<p>Unlike face-to-face teams, creating and sustaining mental models is harder in virtual environments. Leaders must therefore compensate for challenges such as communication barriers and cultural differences. These issues can impact relationship building, which is essential for developing and sustaining shared mental models.</p>
<p>As underlined in <span class="citation" data-cites="Larson2020">(Larson and DeChurch 2020)</span>, face-to-face teams tend to have stronger shared mental models than virtual ones.</p>
<p>To improve team effectiveness and performance in virtual settings, leaders should aim to create a conducive environment for shared mental models. This can be achieved by:</p>
<ul>
<li>Cultivating high-quality, interpersonal communication.<br>
</li>
<li>Creating psychological safety.<br>
</li>
<li>Adopting a leadership style that aligns well with virtual collaboration <span class="citation" data-cites="Larson2020">(Larson and DeChurch 2020)</span>.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="leaderships-role-in-building-a-shared-mind" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="leaderships-role-in-building-a-shared-mind">Leadership’s Role in Building a Shared Mind</h2>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Lungeanu2022">Lungeanu, DeChurch, and Contractor (2022)</span> highlight that leadership particularly <strong>shared leadership</strong> plays a crucial role in creating and shaping shared mental models in teams. This applies to both face-to-face and virtual teams.</p>
<p>For instance, <span class="citation" data-cites="Lungeanu2022">(Lungeanu, DeChurch, and Contractor 2022)</span> note that when leadership responsibilities are shared among members, the team tends to show greater commitment and information sharing. This dynamic fosters trust and enhances performance.</p>
<p>Teams that embrace shared leadership and have diverse skills, experiences, and perspectives are more likely to develop and maintain strong shared mental models.</p>
<p>Furthermore, <strong>connected leadership</strong> as opposed to fragmented leadership offers several advantages for improving similarity in team mental models. It promotes accuracy, synchronization of effort, and cohesion or trust.</p>
<p>For example, <span class="citation" data-cites="Lungeanu2022">(Lungeanu, DeChurch, and Contractor 2022)</span> argue that hierarchical and coordinated leadership are better at promoting shared mental models than factional or isolated forms of leadership. They also emphasize that boundaries among members of shared leadership groups are permeable, allowing reciprocal leadership processes that reduce conflict and tension.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Ultimately, a shared mental model is not just a nice-to-have; it’s the cognitive foundation upon which effective teams are built. It serves as the shared “map” that enables a group of individuals to navigate complex tasks together with clarity and confidence.</p>
<p>While the rise of virtual work presents new challenges, the core principle remains: <strong>effective leadership is the catalyst</strong>. By fostering open communication, psychological safety, and a connected leadership structure, leaders can intentionally design the conditions for these powerful shared understandings to emerge and thrive.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-Larson2020" class="csl-entry">
Larson, Lindsay, and Leslie A. DeChurch. 2020. <span>“Leading Teams in the Digital Age: Four Perspectives on Technology and What They Mean for Leading Teams.”</span> <em>The Leadership Quarterly</em> 31 (1): 101377. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.leaqua.2019.101377">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.leaqua.2019.101377</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Lungeanu2022" class="csl-entry">
Lungeanu, Alina, Leslie A. DeChurch, and Noshir S. Contractor. 2022. <span>“Leading Teams over Time Through Space: Computational Experiments on Leadership Network Archetypes.”</span> <em>The Leadership Quarterly</em>, January, 101595. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.leaqua.2021.101595">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.leaqua.2021.101595</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Schelble2022" class="csl-entry">
Schelble, Beau G., Christopher Flathmann, Nathan J. McNeese, Guo Freeman, and Rohit Mallick. 2022. <span>“Let<span></span>s Think Together! Assessing Shared Mental Models, Performance, and Trust in Human-Agent Teams.”</span> <em>Proceedings of the <span>ACM</span> on Human-Computer Interaction</em> 6 (<span>GROUP</span>): 1–29. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3492832">https://doi.org/10.1145/3492832</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-faustine2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Faustine, Anthony. 2024. <span>“Shared Mental Models: The Invisible
Architecture of High-Performance Teams.”</span> July 12, 2024. <a href="https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/07/">https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/07/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Team leadership</category>
  <category>Leadership</category>
  <guid>https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/07/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/07/team-mental-model.svg" medium="image" type="image/svg+xml"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Lone Wolf vs. The Pack: Why Your Change Strategy Is Failing</title>
  <dc:creator>Anthony Faustine</dc:creator>
  <link>https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/06/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="the-lone-wolf-vs.-the-pack" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-lone-wolf-vs.-the-pack">The Lone Wolf vs.&nbsp;The Pack</h2>
<p>Most change efforts fail not because people resist, but because leaders target the wrong unit of change the individual. As Kurt Lewin showed, transformation begins not with lone heroes, but with the <strong>social forces of the group</strong>. Understanding this shift from motivating individuals to mobilizing teams is the key to making change stick.</p>
</section>
<section id="introduction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>Change is the only constant in today’s global business environment. Yet despite endless meetings, emails, and training sessions, many organizations still struggle to make change stick <span class="citation" data-cites="al2015integrating">(Al-Haddad and Kotnour 2015)</span>. Leaders pour effort into motivating individuals, only to watch employees slip back into old habits.</p>
<p>The problem is not a lack of effort, it is a flaw in perspective. Too many change strategies focus on individuals, treating transformation as a personal mindset issue rather than a collective movement. It is the <em>lone wolf</em> approach to change: trying to inspire one person at a time while ignoring the social currents that shape behavior.</p>
<p>As social psychologist <strong>Kurt Lewin</strong> discovered decades ago, the real force behind sustainable change is not found in individual effort, it lies in the <strong>group dynamic</strong>, the pack. Understanding how groups form, interact, and influence one another can transform the way organizations lead change today.</p>
<p>This post revisits Lewin’s insights on group dynamics and explores how leaders can shift from managing people in isolation to mobilizing the collective energy of their teams.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-heart-of-the-matter-target-the-group-not-the-individual" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-heart-of-the-matter-target-the-group-not-the-individual">The Heart of the Matter: Target the Group, Not the Individual</h2>
<p>At the core of Kurt Lewin’s work is a groundbreaking argument: <strong>meaningful change doesn’t happen at the individual level, but at the group level.</strong> According to Lewin, group behaviour is shaped by a field of forces and symbolic interactions that dictate the group’s structure and, in turn, modify individual behaviour <span class="citation" data-cites="burnes2007kurt">(Burnes 2007)</span>.</p>
<p>Why is the group the primary focus? Because an individual even one open to change is constantly under immense group pressure to conform to existing norms. These group routines and patterns are not just passive habits; they are actively valued and enforced by the group to maintain stability <span class="citation" data-cites="burnes2007kurt">(Burnes 2007)</span>.</p>
<p>This aligns with modern findings, such as Kotter’s, that resistance is more likely to arise from the <strong>system and its ingrained norms</strong> than from isolated individuals <span class="citation" data-cites="al2015integrating">(Al-Haddad and Kotnour 2015)</span>. Therefore, any effective change strategy must concentrate on influencing the team’s <strong>collective norms, roles, and values</strong>.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-prerequisite-creating-a-felt-need-for-change" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-prerequisite-creating-a-felt-need-for-change">The Prerequisite: Creating a “Felt Need” for Change</h2>
<p>Before any change can begin, a critical prerequisite must be met: there must be a <strong>felt need</strong>. This is the deep, internal realization, both at the individual and group levels that the current way of doing things is no longer sufficient and that change is necessary <span class="citation" data-cites="burnes2004kurt burnes2007kurt">(Burnes 2004, 2007)</span>.</p>
<p>If the collective felt-need within a group or organization is low, introducing change becomes problematic. You cannot impose transformation on a group that does not perceive a problem. Lewin argued that successful change begins with engaging group members, helping them understand the <em>why</em> behind the change, and fostering a shared commitment to move forward.</p>
<p>This “felt need” is not merely emotional; it represents a psychological <strong>unfreezing</strong> of the group’s current norms and equilibrium. Without this shared readiness, even the best-designed change initiatives are likely to fail.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-method-action-research-and-collaborative-change" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-method-action-research-and-collaborative-change">The Method: Action Research and Collaborative Change</h2>
<p>Understanding group behaviour is one thing; changing it is another. Lewin’s framework is not just theoretical it is profoundly practical. He proposed a participative method known as <strong>Action Research</strong>, a cyclical process for diagnosing and addressing organisational challenges <span class="citation" data-cites="burnes2004kurt burnes2007kurt">(Burnes 2004, 2007)</span>.</p>
<p>Action Research emphasises that effective change is achieved <em>with</em> people, not <em>to</em> people. It involves a series of iterative steps that make the change process collaborative and adaptive:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Analyze the situation:</strong> The group collaboratively diagnoses the problem, identifying underlying issues that influence behaviour.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Identify alternatives:</strong> Members discuss and explore possible solutions.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Choose and act:</strong> The group selects and implements the most appropriate solution.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Reflect and repeat:</strong> Results are evaluated, and the process is refined based on collective learning.</li>
</ol>
<p>This method reflects Lewin’s belief that behaviour can only be understood and modified within a group context. It embodies the principle of <strong>self-management</strong>, where groups play an active role in shaping their own behaviour <span class="citation" data-cites="burnes2004kurt">(Burnes 2004)</span>. Change, therefore, becomes a participative and collaborative process — one that transforms <strong>resistance into ownership</strong>.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-framework-lewins-3-step-model-for-group-transformation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-framework-lewins-3-step-model-for-group-transformation">The Framework: Lewin’s 3-Step Model for Group Transformation</h2>
<p>With the group engaged and a collaborative process in motion, Lewin proposed that organisational change unfolds through his well-known <strong>3-Step Model</strong> <span class="citation" data-cites="burnes2004kurt">(Burnes 2004)</span>:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Unfreeze:</strong> This stage creates the felt need for change by disrupting existing norms, routines, and assumptions. It prepares the group to let go of old patterns and accept that change is necessary.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Change (Move):</strong> Guided by the principles of Action Research, the group develops and adopts new behaviours, attitudes, and values. This is the implementation phase, where learning and experimentation take place.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Refreeze:</strong> The final stage solidifies the new equilibrium. New group norms are embedded in organisational culture and supported by systems and shared values, ensuring the change endures.</li>
</ol>
<p>Lewin believed that because individuals are inherently influenced by group norms and social forces, sustainable transformation must occur at the group level not solely at the level of individual behaviour <span class="citation" data-cites="al2015integrating">(Al-Haddad and Kotnour 2015)</span>. As he noted, group routines and patterns have intrinsic value; they’re not merely the product of opposing forces but serve a positive function in maintaining <strong>group identity and cohesion</strong> <span class="citation" data-cites="burnes2004kurt burnes2007kurt">(Burnes 2004, 2007)</span>.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-modern-reflection-is-refreezing-still-relevant" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-modern-reflection-is-refreezing-still-relevant">A Modern Reflection: Is Refreezing Still Relevant?</h2>
<p>While Lewin’s model remains foundational, modern change scholars question whether the concept of “refreezing” fits today’s rapidly changing business environment. In an age of constant disruption and agile methodologies, achieving a stable equilibrium may seem unrealistic.</p>
<p>Contemporary perspectives suggest that organisations should cultivate a culture of <strong>continuous learning and adaptability</strong> a state of being “permanently unfrozen.” Nevertheless, Lewin’s insight into the power of <strong>group dynamics</strong> remains timeless. Whether or not we “refreeze,” successful change still depends on engaging the <strong>collective forces</strong> that shape how people think, feel, and act together.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>The enduring genius of Kurt Lewin’s work is its simple, powerful truth: organizations don’t change, people do but people change most effectively in groups. Your next change initiative will succeed or fail based on your ability to look past individual behaviours and see the powerful, invisible currents of group norms, pressures, and values. To change the individual, you must first have the courage to engage, understand, and transform the group. <strong>So, is your organization empowering lone wolves — or building a stronger pack?</strong></p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-al2015integrating" class="csl-entry">
Al-Haddad, Serina, and Timothy Kotnour. 2015. <span>“Integrating the Organizational Change Literature: A Model for Successful Change.”</span> <em>Journal of Organizational Change Management</em> 28 (2): 234–62.
</div>
<div id="ref-burnes2004kurt" class="csl-entry">
Burnes, Bernard. 2004. <span>“Kurt Lewin and the Planned Approach to Change: A Re-Appraisal.”</span> <em>Journal of Management Studies</em> 41 (6): 977–1002.
</div>
<div id="ref-burnes2007kurt" class="csl-entry">
———. 2007. <span>“Kurt Lewin and the Harwood Studies: The Foundations of OD.”</span> <em>The Journal of Applied Behavioral Science</em> 43 (2): 213–31.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-faustine2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Faustine, Anthony. 2024. <span>“The Lone Wolf Vs. The Pack: Why Your
Change Strategy Is Failing.”</span> June 12, 2024. <a href="https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/06/">https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/06/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Change Management</category>
  <category>Leadership</category>
  <guid>https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/06/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/06/change.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
