<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Anthony Faustine&#39;s blog</title>
<link>https://sambaiga.github.io/atom.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://sambaiga.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Anthony Faustine&#39;s blog</description>
<language>en</language>
<generator>quarto-1.8.26</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 23:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Shared Mental Models: The Invisible Architecture of High-Performance Teams</title>
  <dc:creator>Anthony Faustine</dc:creator>
  <link>https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/07/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="introduction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>Ever been on a team where everything just <em>clicks</em>? communication is effortless, everyone knows their role, and the team anticipates each other’s moves, achieving goals with remarkable efficiency. This seamless collaboration is not a magic. It is often the result of something called a <strong>shared mental model</strong>, the invisible architecture that supports high-performance teamwork.</p>
<p>This post explores what shared mental models are, why they are a critical predictor of team effectiveness, and how leaders can consciously cultivate them, especially in the complex environments of virtual and hybrid teams.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-is-a-shared-mental-model" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-a-shared-mental-model">What is a Shared Mental Model?</h2>
<p>Team effectiveness and coordination are critical aspects of a high-performance team. Team members who share a similar and organized understanding of team tasks and goals — and who understand each other’s working environments — are more likely to perform well.</p>
<p>This shared understanding and knowledge about the mission, goals, and other relevant environments among team members are called <strong>mental models</strong>. The shared mental model is one of the most frequently used concepts in team cognition <span class="citation" data-cites="Schelble2022">(Schelble et al. 2022)</span>. <span class="citation" data-cites="Lungeanu2022">(2022)</span> further identify the shared mental model as a critical predictor of team effectiveness.</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Lungeanu2022">Lungeanu, DeChurch, and Contractor (2022)</span> define shared mental models as team properties reflecting how team members organize knowledge and understanding about the team’s purpose, the nature of the work, and how they work together. Thus, team mental models are a collective mental representation among team members of how they interact in performing task-work <span class="citation" data-cites="Larson2020">(Larson and DeChurch 2020)</span>.</p>
<p>They represent the organized mental representations of the various component pieces relevant to a team’s overall task <span class="citation" data-cites="Schelble2022">(Schelble et al. 2022)</span>. As <span class="citation" data-cites="Schelble2022">(Schelble et al. 2022)</span> point out, shared mental models measure whether or not team members share a common understanding of their shared tasks, roles, interdependencies, and strategies.</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Schelble2022">Schelble et al. (2022)</span> break shared mental models into two types:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Task mental model</strong> — covers aspects specific to understanding and completing a shared task.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Team mental model</strong> — focuses on factors related to cooperation and communication within a team.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="the-impact-on-team-success" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-impact-on-team-success">The Impact on Team Success</h2>
<p>Shared mental models can continually develop over time, becoming more effective and influencing various team outcomes, such as objective performance, team viability, member well-being, and strategic alignment <span class="citation" data-cites="Lungeanu2022">(Lungeanu, DeChurch, and Contractor 2022)</span>.</p>
<p>Teams with shared mental models can recognize one another’s needs and information requirements <span class="citation" data-cites="Lungeanu2022 Schelble2022">(Lungeanu, DeChurch, and Contractor 2022; Schelble et al. 2022)</span>, which enhances coordination and mutual support.</p>
<p>While this may be more intuitive in physical teams, virtual teams — now an integral part of modern work — require special attention in developing and maintaining shared mental models among members.</p>
<p>Unlike face-to-face teams, creating and sustaining mental models is harder in virtual environments. Leaders must therefore compensate for challenges such as communication barriers and cultural differences. These issues can impact relationship building, which is essential for developing and sustaining shared mental models.</p>
<p>As underlined in <span class="citation" data-cites="Larson2020">(Larson and DeChurch 2020)</span>, face-to-face teams tend to have stronger shared mental models than virtual ones.</p>
<p>To improve team effectiveness and performance in virtual settings, leaders should aim to create a conducive environment for shared mental models. This can be achieved by:</p>
<ul>
<li>Cultivating high-quality, interpersonal communication.<br>
</li>
<li>Creating psychological safety.<br>
</li>
<li>Adopting a leadership style that aligns well with virtual collaboration <span class="citation" data-cites="Larson2020">(Larson and DeChurch 2020)</span>.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="leaderships-role-in-building-a-shared-mind" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="leaderships-role-in-building-a-shared-mind">Leadership’s Role in Building a Shared Mind</h2>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Lungeanu2022">Lungeanu, DeChurch, and Contractor (2022)</span> highlight that leadership particularly <strong>shared leadership</strong> plays a crucial role in creating and shaping shared mental models in teams. This applies to both face-to-face and virtual teams.</p>
<p>For instance, <span class="citation" data-cites="Lungeanu2022">(Lungeanu, DeChurch, and Contractor 2022)</span> note that when leadership responsibilities are shared among members, the team tends to show greater commitment and information sharing. This dynamic fosters trust and enhances performance.</p>
<p>Teams that embrace shared leadership and have diverse skills, experiences, and perspectives are more likely to develop and maintain strong shared mental models.</p>
<p>Furthermore, <strong>connected leadership</strong> as opposed to fragmented leadership offers several advantages for improving similarity in team mental models. It promotes accuracy, synchronization of effort, and cohesion or trust.</p>
<p>For example, <span class="citation" data-cites="Lungeanu2022">(Lungeanu, DeChurch, and Contractor 2022)</span> argue that hierarchical and coordinated leadership are better at promoting shared mental models than factional or isolated forms of leadership. They also emphasize that boundaries among members of shared leadership groups are permeable, allowing reciprocal leadership processes that reduce conflict and tension.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Ultimately, a shared mental model is not just a nice-to-have; it’s the cognitive foundation upon which effective teams are built. It serves as the shared “map” that enables a group of individuals to navigate complex tasks together with clarity and confidence.</p>
<p>While the rise of virtual work presents new challenges, the core principle remains: <strong>effective leadership is the catalyst</strong>. By fostering open communication, psychological safety, and a connected leadership structure, leaders can intentionally design the conditions for these powerful shared understandings to emerge and thrive.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-Larson2020" class="csl-entry">
Larson, Lindsay, and Leslie A. DeChurch. 2020. <span>“Leading Teams in the Digital Age: Four Perspectives on Technology and What They Mean for Leading Teams.”</span> <em>The Leadership Quarterly</em> 31 (1): 101377. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.leaqua.2019.101377">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.leaqua.2019.101377</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Lungeanu2022" class="csl-entry">
Lungeanu, Alina, Leslie A. DeChurch, and Noshir S. Contractor. 2022. <span>“Leading Teams over Time Through Space: Computational Experiments on Leadership Network Archetypes.”</span> <em>The Leadership Quarterly</em>, January, 101595. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.leaqua.2021.101595">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.leaqua.2021.101595</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Schelble2022" class="csl-entry">
Schelble, Beau G., Christopher Flathmann, Nathan J. McNeese, Guo Freeman, and Rohit Mallick. 2022. <span>“Let<span></span>s Think Together! Assessing Shared Mental Models, Performance, and Trust in Human-Agent Teams.”</span> <em>Proceedings of the <span>ACM</span> on Human-Computer Interaction</em> 6 (<span>GROUP</span>): 1–29. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3492832">https://doi.org/10.1145/3492832</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-faustine2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Faustine, Anthony. 2024. <span>“Shared Mental Models: The Invisible
Architecture of High-Performance Teams.”</span> July 12, 2024. <a href="https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/07/">https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/07/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Team leadership</category>
  <category>Leadership</category>
  <guid>https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/07/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/07/team-mental-model.svg" medium="image" type="image/svg+xml"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Lone Wolf vs. The Pack: Why Your Change Strategy Is Failing</title>
  <dc:creator>Anthony Faustine</dc:creator>
  <link>https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/06/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="the-lone-wolf-vs.-the-pack" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-lone-wolf-vs.-the-pack">The Lone Wolf vs.&nbsp;The Pack</h2>
<p>Most change efforts fail not because people resist, but because leaders target the wrong unit of change the individual. As Kurt Lewin showed, transformation begins not with lone heroes, but with the <strong>social forces of the group</strong>. Understanding this shift from motivating individuals to mobilizing teams is the key to making change stick.</p>
</section>
<section id="introduction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>Change is the only constant in today’s global business environment. Yet despite endless meetings, emails, and training sessions, many organizations still struggle to make change stick <span class="citation" data-cites="al2015integrating">(Al-Haddad and Kotnour 2015)</span>. Leaders pour effort into motivating individuals, only to watch employees slip back into old habits.</p>
<p>The problem is not a lack of effort, it is a flaw in perspective. Too many change strategies focus on individuals, treating transformation as a personal mindset issue rather than a collective movement. It is the <em>lone wolf</em> approach to change: trying to inspire one person at a time while ignoring the social currents that shape behavior.</p>
<p>As social psychologist <strong>Kurt Lewin</strong> discovered decades ago, the real force behind sustainable change is not found in individual effort, it lies in the <strong>group dynamic</strong>, the pack. Understanding how groups form, interact, and influence one another can transform the way organizations lead change today.</p>
<p>This post revisits Lewin’s insights on group dynamics and explores how leaders can shift from managing people in isolation to mobilizing the collective energy of their teams.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-heart-of-the-matter-target-the-group-not-the-individual" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-heart-of-the-matter-target-the-group-not-the-individual">The Heart of the Matter: Target the Group, Not the Individual</h2>
<p>At the core of Kurt Lewin’s work is a groundbreaking argument: <strong>meaningful change doesn’t happen at the individual level, but at the group level.</strong> According to Lewin, group behaviour is shaped by a field of forces and symbolic interactions that dictate the group’s structure and, in turn, modify individual behaviour <span class="citation" data-cites="burnes2007kurt">(Burnes 2007)</span>.</p>
<p>Why is the group the primary focus? Because an individual even one open to change is constantly under immense group pressure to conform to existing norms. These group routines and patterns are not just passive habits; they are actively valued and enforced by the group to maintain stability <span class="citation" data-cites="burnes2007kurt">(Burnes 2007)</span>.</p>
<p>This aligns with modern findings, such as Kotter’s, that resistance is more likely to arise from the <strong>system and its ingrained norms</strong> than from isolated individuals <span class="citation" data-cites="al2015integrating">(Al-Haddad and Kotnour 2015)</span>. Therefore, any effective change strategy must concentrate on influencing the team’s <strong>collective norms, roles, and values</strong>.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-prerequisite-creating-a-felt-need-for-change" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-prerequisite-creating-a-felt-need-for-change">The Prerequisite: Creating a “Felt Need” for Change</h2>
<p>Before any change can begin, a critical prerequisite must be met: there must be a <strong>felt need</strong>. This is the deep, internal realization, both at the individual and group levels that the current way of doing things is no longer sufficient and that change is necessary <span class="citation" data-cites="burnes2004kurt burnes2007kurt">(Burnes 2004, 2007)</span>.</p>
<p>If the collective felt-need within a group or organization is low, introducing change becomes problematic. You cannot impose transformation on a group that does not perceive a problem. Lewin argued that successful change begins with engaging group members, helping them understand the <em>why</em> behind the change, and fostering a shared commitment to move forward.</p>
<p>This “felt need” is not merely emotional; it represents a psychological <strong>unfreezing</strong> of the group’s current norms and equilibrium. Without this shared readiness, even the best-designed change initiatives are likely to fail.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-method-action-research-and-collaborative-change" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-method-action-research-and-collaborative-change">The Method: Action Research and Collaborative Change</h2>
<p>Understanding group behaviour is one thing; changing it is another. Lewin’s framework is not just theoretical it is profoundly practical. He proposed a participative method known as <strong>Action Research</strong>, a cyclical process for diagnosing and addressing organisational challenges <span class="citation" data-cites="burnes2004kurt burnes2007kurt">(Burnes 2004, 2007)</span>.</p>
<p>Action Research emphasises that effective change is achieved <em>with</em> people, not <em>to</em> people. It involves a series of iterative steps that make the change process collaborative and adaptive:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Analyze the situation:</strong> The group collaboratively diagnoses the problem, identifying underlying issues that influence behaviour.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Identify alternatives:</strong> Members discuss and explore possible solutions.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Choose and act:</strong> The group selects and implements the most appropriate solution.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Reflect and repeat:</strong> Results are evaluated, and the process is refined based on collective learning.</li>
</ol>
<p>This method reflects Lewin’s belief that behaviour can only be understood and modified within a group context. It embodies the principle of <strong>self-management</strong>, where groups play an active role in shaping their own behaviour <span class="citation" data-cites="burnes2004kurt">(Burnes 2004)</span>. Change, therefore, becomes a participative and collaborative process — one that transforms <strong>resistance into ownership</strong>.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-framework-lewins-3-step-model-for-group-transformation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-framework-lewins-3-step-model-for-group-transformation">The Framework: Lewin’s 3-Step Model for Group Transformation</h2>
<p>With the group engaged and a collaborative process in motion, Lewin proposed that organisational change unfolds through his well-known <strong>3-Step Model</strong> <span class="citation" data-cites="burnes2004kurt">(Burnes 2004)</span>:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Unfreeze:</strong> This stage creates the felt need for change by disrupting existing norms, routines, and assumptions. It prepares the group to let go of old patterns and accept that change is necessary.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Change (Move):</strong> Guided by the principles of Action Research, the group develops and adopts new behaviours, attitudes, and values. This is the implementation phase, where learning and experimentation take place.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Refreeze:</strong> The final stage solidifies the new equilibrium. New group norms are embedded in organisational culture and supported by systems and shared values, ensuring the change endures.</li>
</ol>
<p>Lewin believed that because individuals are inherently influenced by group norms and social forces, sustainable transformation must occur at the group level not solely at the level of individual behaviour <span class="citation" data-cites="al2015integrating">(Al-Haddad and Kotnour 2015)</span>. As he noted, group routines and patterns have intrinsic value; they’re not merely the product of opposing forces but serve a positive function in maintaining <strong>group identity and cohesion</strong> <span class="citation" data-cites="burnes2004kurt burnes2007kurt">(Burnes 2004, 2007)</span>.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-modern-reflection-is-refreezing-still-relevant" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-modern-reflection-is-refreezing-still-relevant">A Modern Reflection: Is Refreezing Still Relevant?</h2>
<p>While Lewin’s model remains foundational, modern change scholars question whether the concept of “refreezing” fits today’s rapidly changing business environment. In an age of constant disruption and agile methodologies, achieving a stable equilibrium may seem unrealistic.</p>
<p>Contemporary perspectives suggest that organisations should cultivate a culture of <strong>continuous learning and adaptability</strong> a state of being “permanently unfrozen.” Nevertheless, Lewin’s insight into the power of <strong>group dynamics</strong> remains timeless. Whether or not we “refreeze,” successful change still depends on engaging the <strong>collective forces</strong> that shape how people think, feel, and act together.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>The enduring genius of Kurt Lewin’s work is its simple, powerful truth: organizations don’t change, people do but people change most effectively in groups. Your next change initiative will succeed or fail based on your ability to look past individual behaviours and see the powerful, invisible currents of group norms, pressures, and values. To change the individual, you must first have the courage to engage, understand, and transform the group. <strong>So, is your organization empowering lone wolves — or building a stronger pack?</strong></p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-al2015integrating" class="csl-entry">
Al-Haddad, Serina, and Timothy Kotnour. 2015. <span>“Integrating the Organizational Change Literature: A Model for Successful Change.”</span> <em>Journal of Organizational Change Management</em> 28 (2): 234–62.
</div>
<div id="ref-burnes2004kurt" class="csl-entry">
Burnes, Bernard. 2004. <span>“Kurt Lewin and the Planned Approach to Change: A Re-Appraisal.”</span> <em>Journal of Management Studies</em> 41 (6): 977–1002.
</div>
<div id="ref-burnes2007kurt" class="csl-entry">
———. 2007. <span>“Kurt Lewin and the Harwood Studies: The Foundations of OD.”</span> <em>The Journal of Applied Behavioral Science</em> 43 (2): 213–31.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-faustine2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Faustine, Anthony. 2024. <span>“The Lone Wolf Vs. The Pack: Why Your
Change Strategy Is Failing.”</span> June 12, 2024. <a href="https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/06/">https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/06/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Change Management</category>
  <category>Leadership</category>
  <guid>https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/06/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/06/change.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
