<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Anthony Faustine&#39;s blog</title>
<link>https://sambaiga.github.io/atom.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://sambaiga.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Anthony Faustine&#39;s blog</description>
<language>en</language>
<generator>quarto-1.8.25</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>A Year of Growth: 13 Books That Transformed My Perspective in 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Anthony Faustine</dc:creator>
  <link>https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2025/01/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="introduction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>At the beginning of 2024, I set a personal goal: to read one book each month. This was fueled by my desire to keep learning, expand my thinking, and deepen my self-awareness.</p>
<p>The journey had its highs and lows. Some months, I breezed through stories that gripped me from the start. Other times, staying on track demanded discipline and focus, as distractions tested my resolve. Yet, I remained committed, motivated by the belief that each book brought me closer to growth and self-discovery.</p>
<p>By the end of the year, I had completed 13 books; a testament to the power of persistence and the commitment I made at the start of this journey. Each book left its mark, shaping my thinking and broadening my perspective in unexpected ways. In this post, I’ll share my reading list and reflect on how these stories and ideas enriched my year. I invite you to join me in exploring the lessons learned and the insights gained from this rewarding experience.</p>
</section>
<section id="book-covered" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="book-covered">Book covered</h2>
<section id="build-by-tony-fadell" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="build-by-tony-fadell">Build by Tony Fadell</h3>
<p>In <strong>Build</strong> <img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1652120231i/59696349.jpg" alt="Build Book Cover" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;">, Tony Fadell offers an unconventional guide to product development, entrepreneurship, and leadership, drawing on his extensive experience in Silicon Valley as the creator of the iPod and founder of Nest. The book serves as a practical and insightful roadmap for innovators, designers, and product managers, making it a valuable resource for anyone looking to navigate the complexities of bringing ideas to life.</p>
<p>Fadell emphasizes the importance of <strong>purpose-driven product development</strong>, advocating for solutions that genuinely improve users’ lives. This focus on purpose resonates with me, as it highlights the need to create products that not only meet market demands but also enhance the quality of life for users. He encourages readers to embrace continuous learning, urging us to remain curious and glean insights from both successes and failures. This mindset is crucial in a rapidly changing environment where adaptability is key.</p>
<p>Another key theme in the book is the <strong>value of simplicity in design</strong>. Fadell urges creators to eliminate unnecessary features and focus on delivering core value. This principle has inspired me to evaluate my own projects and consider how I can streamline processes to enhance user experience without overwhelming them with complexity.</p>
<p>Additionally, Fadell champions a leadership style rooted in empathy, fostering a safe environment for experimentation and supporting team growth. This approach is refreshing and underscores the importance of <strong>building strong relationships within teams</strong> to encourage innovation.</p>
<p>Through candid anecdotes, mistakes, and hard-won lessons from his journeys at Apple and Nest, Fadell provides an authentic and relatable guide for aspiring entrepreneurs, product creators, and leaders. Fadell’s insights have motivated me to approach my own projects with a renewed focus on purpose, simplicity, and empathy, ultimately leading to more impactful and meaningful outcomes.</p>
<p><strong>Key lesson</strong>: successful product development requires a deep understanding of user needs, a relentless pursuit of simplicity, a culture of continuous learning, and a leadership style that fosters creativity and empowers team.</p>
</section>
<section id="essentialism-by-greg-mckeown" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="essentialism-by-greg-mckeown">Essentialism by Greg McKeown</h3>
<p>In <strong>Essentialism</strong> <img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1403165375i/18077875.jpg" align="left" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;">, Greg McKeown presents a disciplined approach to identifying and prioritizing what truly matters in our lives. The book serves as both a wake-up call and a roadmap for individuals like me overwhelmed by competing demands and distractions. McKeown emphasizes the transformative power of <strong>less but better</strong> encouraging readers to focus on their highest point of contribution.</p>
<p><strong>Key Lesson:</strong> Clarity about priorities opens the door to greater freedom and fulfillment. Life is filled with trade-offs, and the path to true success lies in making intentional, wise choices that align with what truly matters.</p>
<p>By systematically eliminating non-essential tasks and distractions, McKeown guides readers in protecting their most valuable resources—time, energy, attention, and well-being. This essentialist mindset empowers individuals to make intentional choices and concentrate on activities that genuinely enhance their lives, leading to greater fulfillment and success. I find this approach liberating, as it encourages me to focus on what brings the most value rather than getting caught up in the noise of everyday life.</p>
<p>The book also highlights the importance of <strong>saying no</strong> to non essential commitments, which can be challenging but ultimately leads to a more fulfilling and productive life. Embracing this mindset has inspired me to evaluate my commitments and ensure they align with my core values and long-term goals.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-magic-of-thinking-big-by-david-schwartz" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-magic-of-thinking-big-by-david-schwartz">The Magic of Thinking Big by David Schwartz</h3>
<p>The <strong>Magic of Thinking Big</strong> <img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1404632064i/759945.jpg" align="left" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;"> by David J. Schwartz is a timeless reminder that success isn’t solely reserved for the most gifted. It’s a testament to the power of mindset. Those who dare to dream big, believe in themselves, and take intentional action are most likely to achieve their goals. This book profoundly impacted my thinking, project me to expand my mindset, overcome limiting beliefs, and cultivate habits that align with my aspirations for greatness.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the book emphasizes the importance of treating others with respect, learning from setbacks, and embracing continuous learning as essential for a successful and fulfilling life. This resonates with me, as it highlights that growth often comes from our experiences, both positive and negative.</p>
<p><strong>Key lessons</strong>: Success is primarily a product of mindset – believing in yourself, cultivating a positive attitude, and taking consistent action towards your goals, regardless of inherent talent or luck.</p>
</section>
<section id="same-as-ever-by-morgan-housel" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="same-as-ever-by-morgan-housel">Same As Ever by Morgan Housel</h3>
<p>Morgan Housel’s <strong>Same As Ever</strong> <img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1680687321i/125116554.jpg" align="left" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;"> provides a compelling framework for understanding the enduring nature of human behavior. Despite the rapid pace of change in our world, Housel argues that our core emotions, desires, and behaviors remain remarkably consistent.</p>
<p>Housel emphasizes the concept of <strong>rational optimism</strong>, which involves recognizing both the potential for growth and the inevitability of challenges. This balanced perspective encourages us to adhere to core principles like integrity and patience while also acknowledging the inherent strengths and weaknesses of human nature. I find this approach refreshing, as it promotes a realistic yet hopeful outlook on life.</p>
<p>The book explores how fundamental human emotions—such as fear, greed, and hope continue to drive our actions, regardless of the technological and social changes surrounding us. This idea serves as a reminder that while the world may evolve, the essence of what it means to be human remains constant. Housel’s insights encourage us to focus on these timeless aspects of human behavior, which can guide our decisions and interactions in an ever-changing landscape.</p>
<p>By embracing the enduring truths of human nature, we can navigate the complexities of modern life with greater wisdom and resilience. I appreciate Housel’s ability to distill these insights into practical guidance, making this book a valuable resource for anyone seeking to foster a balanced and optimistic approach to life.</p>
<p><strong>Key lesson</strong> understanding the enduring nature of human behavior, while embracing rational optimism and core principles is essential for navigating life’s complexities and fostering meaningful relationships.</p>
</section>
<section id="never-split-the-difference-by-chris-voss" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="never-split-the-difference-by-chris-voss">Never Split the Difference by Chris Voss</h3>
<p><strong>Never Split the Difference</strong> <img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1680014152i/123857637.jpg" align="left" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;"> by Chris Voss, a former FBI hostage negotiator, offers unique insights into the art of negotiation that have completely shifted my perspective on the subject. This book illustrates how powerful negotiation can be, not just in high-stakes situations but also in everyday life.</p>
<p>Voss challenges traditional negotiation strategies that often focus on compromise. Instead, he advocates for <strong>empathy, understanding, and subtle psychological tactics</strong> to achieve optimal outcomes. This approach has taught me that negotiation is less about winning and more about fostering <em>collaboration</em> and <em>curiosity</em>. By prioritizing these elements, I can engage in conversations that lead to more meaningful and productive results.</p>
<p>The book provides practical tools that I can apply in various contexts, whether in professional settings or personal interactions. Voss emphasizes the importance of active listening and emotional intelligence, which are crucial for understanding the needs and motivations of others. This has encouraged me to approach negotiations with a mindset of collaboration rather than confrontation, ultimately leading to better relationships and outcomes.</p>
<p>Through engaging anecdotes and real-life examples, Voss illustrates how these techniques can be effectively implemented. His insights have inspired me to rethink my approach to discussions and negotiations, making me more aware of the dynamics at play.</p>
<p><strong>Key Lesson</strong>: True influence comes from understanding others, not overpowering them.</p>
</section>
<section id="think-again-by-adam-grant" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="think-again-by-adam-grant">Think Again by Adam Grant</h3>
<p>In <strong>Think Again</strong>, <img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1602574232i/55539565.jpg" align="left" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;"> Adam Grant profoundly challenges our assumptions about knowledge and belief, urging readers to cultivate a mindset of <strong>intellectual humility</strong> and curiosity. He defines intellectual humility as recognizing the limitations of our own knowledge and being willing to learn from everyone. This approach fosters open inquiry and leads to better decision-making, which I find incredibly valuable in both personal and professional contexts.</p>
<p>Grant encourages us to approach life with curiosity and openness, advocating for the importance of questioning our beliefs, considering new evidence, testing our assumptions, and holding our ideas loosely. This flexibility allows us to adapt when presented with new information. I particularly resonate with his assertion that being wrong is not a failure; rather, it is an opportunity for learning. When we discover we’re mistaken, we are simply becoming less wrong—a positive step in personal growth.</p>
<p>Furthermore, Grant highlights the significance of separating our identity from our ideas. This separation enables more objective evaluation and reduces defensive reactions when our beliefs are challenged. He introduces the concept of a <strong>challenge network</strong> a group of trusted individuals who provide honest feedback and help us reconsider our perspectives. This idea has inspired me to seek out such a network in my own life, as it can foster deeper understanding and growth.</p>
<p>Grant’s approach to learning and growth resonates deeply with me, as it emphasizes not merely changing one’s mind but creating a life where learning and evolving take precedence over the need to <em>always be right</em>. This shift in perspective is crucial for personal growth, fostering innovation, and cultivating meaningful relationships.</p>
<p>Overall, <em>Think Again</em> serves as a powerful reminder of the importance of intellectual humility and the continuous journey of self-improvement. I look forward to applying these principles as I navigate my own beliefs and interactions with others.</p>
<p><strong>Key Lesson:</strong> Growth comes from being willing to admit what you don’t know and learning from others.</p>
</section>
<section id="mans-search-for-meaning-by-viktor-e.-frankl" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mans-search-for-meaning-by-viktor-e.-frankl">Man’s Search for Meaning by Viktor E. Frankl</h3>
<p>This profound memoir and philosophical exploration <img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1535419394i/4069.jpg" align="left" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;"> by Viktor Frankl delves into the human capacity to find meaning and purpose even in the face of unimaginable suffering. Drawing upon his own harrowing experiences as a prisoner in Nazi concentration camps, Frankl presents a compelling argument for the human will to survive and the enduring power of the human spirit. His reflections on resilience and purpose have encouraged me to view suffering as an opportunity for growth.</p>
<p>Frankl’s central thesis is that life has meaning under all circumstances, even the most miserable ones. He asserts that our main drive is not pleasure, as Freud suggested, but rather the pursuit of meaning. This <em>will to meaning</em> serves as a fundamental motivation for human behavior, which resonates deeply with me. It has shifted my perspective on challenges, prompting me to seek out the lessons and insights that can emerge from difficult experiences.</p>
<p>Throughout the book, Frankl shares personal anecdotes and observations that illustrate how individuals can choose their attitudes and responses, even in the direst situations. This idea of choosing one’s response is a powerful reminder of our inherent strength and agency, reinforcing the notion that we can find purpose in our suffering.</p>
<p>Moreover, Frankl emphasizes the importance of having a <strong>clear sense of purpose</strong>, which can guide us through life’s adversities. His insights have inspired me to reflect on my own values and aspirations, encouraging me to cultivate a mindset that prioritizes meaning and fulfillment over mere pleasure or comfort.</p>
<p>Overall, Man’s Search for Meaning is a transformative read that offers profound insights into the human experience. Frankl’s ability to articulate the significance of meaning in our lives has not only enriched my understanding of resilience but also motivated me to embrace challenges as opportunities for personal growth and deeper understanding.</p>
<p><strong>Key Lesson</strong>: When you have a “why” to live, you can bear almost any “how.” This powerful insight underscores the importance of having a strong sense of purpose, which can provide the strength needed to endure the most challenging circumstances.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-anxious-generation-by-jonathan-haidt" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-anxious-generation-by-jonathan-haidt">The Anxious Generation by Jonathan Haidt</h3>
<p>In <strong>The Anxious Generation</strong> <img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1711573377i/171681821.jpg" align="left" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;">, Jonathan Haidt presents a deeply researched and thought-provoking examination of the alarming rise in anxiety and depression among young people, particularly Generation Z. His compelling evidence indicates a significant increase in mood disorders among adolescents since the early 2010s, which he links to the widespread adoption of smartphones and social media.</p>
<p>Haidt identifies several key factors contributing to this mental health crisis. First, he discusses <strong>excessive social media use</strong>, citing studies that reveal a correlation between heavy usage, around 3 to 4 hours daily and increased levels of depression and anxiety, especially among girls. This insight has made me reflect on how pervasive social media is in the lives of young people today and the potential consequences it carries.</p>
<p>Another critical aspect of Haidt’s argument is his critique of <strong>overprotective parenting</strong>. He highlights the cultural shift towards <strong>safetyism</strong> which he believes deprives children of essential experiences needed to develop resilience and problem-solving skills. This perspective challenges me to consider how our parenting practices may inadvertently hinder the growth of independence and confidence in young people.</p>
<p>Haidt also contrasts the current <strong>phone based childhood</strong> with the previous <strong>play based childhood</strong>, arguing that this transition has disrupted children’s social interactions and neurological development. This comparison resonates with me, as it underscores the importance of unstructured play and face-to-face interactions in fostering healthy development.</p>
<p>Overall, <em>The Anxious Generation</em> serves as a crucial resource for understanding the mental health challenges facing today’s youth. Haidt’s analysis not only sheds light on the factors contributing to this crisis but also calls for a reevaluation of how we approach parenting and societal expectations in order to foster a healthier, more resilient generation. His exploration of these issues has prompted me to think critically about how we can better support young people in navigating the complexities of modern life.</p>
<p><strong>Key Lesson:</strong> Overemphasis on safety and protection can hinder young people’s resilience and ability to cope with adversity, ultimately making them less prepared to face life’s challenges.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-psychology-of-money-by-morgan-housel" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-psychology-of-money-by-morgan-housel">The Psychology of Money by Morgan Housel</h3>
<p>This book <img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1581527774i/41881472.jpg" align="left" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;"> reshaped the way I think about <strong>money</strong>, <strong>wealth</strong>, and <strong>financial freedom</strong>. Unlike traditional personal finance books that focus on numbers, budgets, or technical strategies, Housel takes a deeply human approach, exploring how our emotions, habits, and perspectives shape our financial decisions.</p>
<p>Housel’s insights helped me understand that money isn’t just about math, it’s about behavior. The way we think about money is influenced by our upbringing, life experiences, and psychological biases, which often leads to decisions that don’t align with logic or long-term goals. This perspective has encouraged me to reflect on my own financial habits and the underlying motivations behind them.</p>
<p>One of the key takeaways from the book is that the biggest value of money isn’t to buy luxury goods but to gain control over your time and life the ultimate form of freedom. This idea has profoundly impacted my view of financial success, shifting my focus from accumulating wealth for its own sake to using it as a tool for achieving a more fulfilling and independent life.</p>
<p>Housel also shares engaging stories that illustrate the strange ways people think about money, making complex concepts accessible and relatable. His emphasis on the importance of patience and long-term thinking has inspired me to adopt a more measured approach to my financial decisions, recognizing that true wealth often comes from consistent, thoughtful actions over time.</p>
<p><strong>Key lesson</strong>: Money is not about what you earn or spend—it’s about the freedom to live life on your terms. true wealth isn’t about flashy cars, expensive vacations, or big houses—it’s about what you don’t see: financial freedom, security, and the ability to make choices without stress.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-forty-rules-of-love-by-elif-shafak" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-forty-rules-of-love-by-elif-shafak">The Forty Rules of Love by Elif Shafak</h3>
<p>Elif Shafak’s <img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1442161289i/6642715.jpg" align="left" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;"> <strong>The Forty Rules of Love</strong> beautifully intertwines themes of love, spirituality, and self-discovery. Through the parallel stories of Ella Rubenstein, a contemporary housewife, and the profound spiritual connection between Rumi and Shams of Tabriz, the novel explores the transformative power of love in its various forms; <strong>divine, romantic, and platonic</strong>.</p>
<p>Shafak emphasizes that true love requires <em>vulnerability</em>, <em>embracing imperfection</em>, and <em>a willingness to let go of control</em>. This perspective has profoundly impacted my understanding of relationships, highlighting that love is not just about connection but also about personal growth and acceptance.</p>
<p>The journey of love, as depicted in the novel, is deeply intertwined with spirituality, suggesting that it is a path of <strong>surrender, trust, and faith</strong>. Furthermore, the novel acknowledges the duality of pain and joy inherent in love, recognizing that <em>pain can be a catalyst for growth and transformation</em>. This insight has encouraged me to embrace the complexities of my own experiences, understanding that challenges can lead to deeper connections and greater self-awareness.</p>
<p>Ultimately, The Forty Rules of Love celebrates the power of stories to heal, connect, and inspire us to live authentically. Shafak’s narrative encourages readers to embrace their unique paths and find meaning in the human experience. The book has inspired me to reflect on my own relationships and the ways in which love can shape our lives, urging me to approach love with an open heart and a willingness to learn.</p>
<p><strong>Key Lesson:</strong> Love, in all its forms, is a journey of transformation that requires vulnerability and courage.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-man-in-the-mirror-by-patrick-morley" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-man-in-the-mirror-by-patrick-morley">The Man in the Mirror by Patrick Morley</h3>
<p>The 25th Anniversary Edition of <strong>The Man in the Mirror</strong> <img src="https://books.google.es/books/publisher/content?id=0Qh0AwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PP1&amp;img=1&amp;zoom=3&amp;hl=en&amp;bul=1&amp;sig=ACfU3U0Hjhw1ETmIQQx9B5CosQUSFIUYDg&amp;w=1280" align="left" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;"> by Patrick Morley is a timeless guide that continues to resonate with men seeking purpose and integrity. Even decades later, Morley’s wisdom remains remarkably relevant, as he has updated the content with fresh insights to address the unique challenges of today’s world.</p>
<p>Through its exploration of 24 key challenges, Morley provides a practical, faith-based framework for navigating issues such as career pressures, spiritual emptiness, broken relationships, and misplaced priorities. This approach has prompted me to reflect on my own life and the various obstacles I face.</p>
<p>One of the most powerful messages in The Man in the Mirror is that <strong>true success is not about what you achieve, but who you become and how you serve others</strong>. This perspective has shifted my understanding of success, urging me to confront my values, goals, and character. Morley also highlights the distractions of modern life, including technology and shifting cultural values, which can easily divert our focus from what truly matters.</p>
<p>Additionally, the book encourages men to consider their <strong>legacy</strong>. Morley emphasizes the importance of leaving a positive impact through service, love, and faith, compelling me to think about how my actions today will resonate in the future.</p>
<p>Overall, The Man in the Mirror serves as an invaluable resource for any man seeking to cultivate a meaningful life rooted in integrity and purpose. I appreciate the insights Morley offers, and I look forward to applying these principles as I strive to make a lasting, positive difference in my own life and the lives of others.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-21-irrefutable-laws-of-leadership-by-john-maxwell" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-21-irrefutable-laws-of-leadership-by-john-maxwell">The 21 Irrefutable Laws of Leadership by John Maxwell</h3>
<p>Reading John C. Maxwell’s <img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1659656057i/61860935.jpg" align="left" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;"> The 21 Irrefutable Laws of Leadership has been one of the most practical and insightful experiences of my year. This timeless guide is incredibly applicable for anyone looking to enhance their leadership skills, whether in the workplace, community, or personal life, as it distills decades of experience into 21 core principles.</p>
<p>What resonated with me the most is Maxwell’s emphasis that true <strong>leadership is about influence</strong>, not authority. He highlights the importance of creating genuine connections and inspiring others to follow, which I believe is crucial in any leadership role. A significant aspect of his approach is the concept of <strong>servant leadership</strong>, which prioritizes the needs of the team. By acknowledging their importance, supporting individual growth, and fostering an empowering environment, leaders can cultivate a more engaged and motivated team.</p>
<p>Maxwell also stresses that trust is the cornerstone of effective leadership. He argues that trust is built on personal character, consistent values, honesty, and the courage to apologize and make amends when necessary. This insight has made me reflect on my own leadership practices and the importance of being trustworthy in all my interactions.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I appreciate Maxwell’s perspective that leadership is a continuous journey of personal development. His assertion that we must commit to lifelong learning and adaptation is a reminder that there is always room for growth, no matter how experienced we may become.</p>
<p>Finally, Maxwell encourages leaders to focus on their long-term impact. This includes developing other leaders, creating lasting positive change, and leading with authenticity and ethical principles. This holistic approach to leadership inspires me to think beyond immediate results and consider how my actions can contribute to a positive legacy.</p>
<p><strong>Key lesson:</strong> Leadership is not about titles—it’s about service and influence.</p>
</section>
<section id="digital-minimalism-choosing-a-focused-life-in-a-noisy-world-by-cal-newport" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="digital-minimalism-choosing-a-focused-life-in-a-noisy-world-by-cal-newport">Digital Minimalism: Choosing a Focused Life in a Noisy World by Cal Newport</h3>
<p>In our hyper-connected world, overflowing with notifications and constant digital distractions,<img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/71PB7ieLx7L._SY522_.jpg" align="left" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;"> Cal Newport’s Digital Minimalism offers a refreshing perspective. Rather than demonizing technology, Newport encourages us to cultivate a more intentional relationship with it. This approach has prompted me to rethink how I interact with digital tools in my daily life.</p>
<p>Newport challenges us to critically examine our technology usage, prioritizing tools that align with our values and eliminating those that detract from our well-being. This idea resonates deeply with me, as it highlights the importance of being mindful about the technology we choose to engage with. His insights have inspired me to assess the impact of various digital platforms on my life, leading to a more discerning approach to my screen time.</p>
<p>The book provides practical strategies for implementing a digital minimalist lifestyle, such as engaging in <strong>digital decluttering</strong> and <strong>establishing technology-free time</strong>. These strategies have encouraged me to set boundaries around my usage, helping me reclaim time for more meaningful activities and connections.</p>
<p>Moreover, Newport emphasizes the significance of real-world interactions and the value of focusing on activities that truly enrich our lives. This perspective has motivated me to seek out experiences that foster deeper connections with others and align more closely with my personal values.</p>
<p>Newport’s emphasis on intentionality has not only reshaped my view of digital tools but also empowered me to take control of my digital habits, fostering a healthier and more fulfilling relationship with technology.</p>
<p><strong>Key lesson:</strong> technology should serve us, not the other way around. By intentionally choosing how we engage with technology and setting clear boundaries, we can reclaim our time, focus, and ultimately, our sense of purpose.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2>
<p>This year’s reading journey has been a transformative experience, filled with diverse perspectives that weave together a powerful narrative about living a meaningful life. Each book offered unique insights, prompting me to re-evaluate my priorities, cultivate resilience, and embrace the power of love in all its forms.</p>
<p>Key themes emerged throughout my reading, particularly the importance of <strong>purpose and intentionality</strong>. Books like <em>Build by Tony Fadell</em> and <em>Essentialism by Greg McKeown</em> emphasized the significance of <strong>starting with “why”</strong> and focusing on <strong>what truly matters</strong>. Fadell’s exploration of product development highlighted the necessity of identifying and solving the right problems, while McKeown’s mantra of <strong>less but better</strong> encouraged me to prioritize ruthlessly and protect my most valuable resources. <em>Digital Minimalism</em> further reinforced the need for intentional living in our digital age.</p>
<p>Several books this year profoundly influenced my thinking, particularly those that emphasized the transformative power of mindset. <em>The Magic of Thinking Big by David J. Schwartz</em> inspired me to believe in myself and embrace a growth mindset, while <em>Think Again by Adam Grant</em> challenged my assumptions and encouraged me to embrace the discomfort of uncertainty. Grant convincingly argues that being wrong isn’t a failure, but rather an opportunity for learning. When we discover our initial beliefs are incorrect, we’re simply becoming less wrong, a crucial step in personal growth. He emphasizes the importance of <strong>intellectual humility</strong>, acknowledging the limitations of our own knowledge and being open to learning from diverse perspectives. This approach fosters open inquiry and leads to better decisionmaking. Both books highlighted the importance of continuous learning and adaptation as essential for personal and professional growth</p>
<p>Resilience emerged as another key theme. <em>Same As Ever by Morgan Housel</em> offered valuable insights into the enduring nature of human behavior, reminding me that while the world changes, core human principles remain constant. <em>The Psychology of Money</em> further emphasized the importance of understanding our emotions and biases in navigating life’s challenges. <em>Jonathan Haidt’s The Anxious Generation</em> highlighted the necessity of fostering resilience, independence, and critical thinking in today’s world. This message resonated deeply with Viktor Frankl’s Man’s Search for Meaning, which serves as a powerful testament to the human spirit’s ability to find meaning and purpose even in the face of unimaginable suffering.</p>
<p>The importance of human connection was evident throughout my reading. <em>Never Split the Difference by Chris Voss</em> emphasized the power of empathy and understanding in communication, while <em>The 21 Irrefutable Laws of Leadership</em> by John C. Maxwell highlighted the significance of service and influence in building meaningful relationships.</p>
<p>Finally, <em>Elif Shafak’s The Forty Rules of Love</em> beautifully explored the transformative power of love in all its forms, reminding me that love requires vulnerability, courage, and a willingness to embrace imperfection.</p>
<p>These books have left a lasting impression, shaping how I think, act, and relate to others. They have reminded me to focus on building a life of purpose, cultivating resilience, and embracing the power of human connection.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-faustine2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Faustine, Anthony. 2025. <span>“A Year of Growth: 13 Books That
Transformed My Perspective in 2024.”</span> January 1, 2025. <a href="https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2025/01/">https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2025/01/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>book</category>
  <guid>https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2025/01/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2025/01/2024_reading_list.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>My 2023 Reading Journey: 11 Books That Shaped My Growth</title>
  <dc:creator>Anthony Faustine</dc:creator>
  <link>https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/01/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="introduction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>At the beginning of 2024, I set a personal goal: to read one book each month. This was fueled by my desire to keep learning, expand my thinking, and deepen my self-awareness.</p>
<p>The journey had its highs and lows. Some months, I breezed through stories that gripped me from the start. Other times, staying on track demanded discipline and focus, as distractions tested my resolve. Yet, I remained committed, motivated by the belief that each book brought me closer to growth and self-discovery.</p>
<p>By the end of the year, I had completed 13 books; a testament to the power of persistence and the commitment I made at the start of this journey. Each book left its mark, shaping my thinking and broadening my perspective in unexpected ways. In this post, I’ll share my reading list and reflect on how these stories and ideas enriched my year. I invite you to join me in exploring the lessons learned and the insights gained from this rewarding experience.</p>
</section>
<section id="book-covered" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="book-covered">Book covered</h2>
<section id="what-got-you-here-wont-get-you-there-by-marshall-goldsmith-and-mark-reiter" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-got-you-here-wont-get-you-there-by-marshall-goldsmith-and-mark-reiter">What Got You Here Won’t Get You There by Marshall Goldsmith and Mark Reiter</h3>
<p>In <strong>What Got You Here Won’t Get You There</strong> <img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/81izlzd-igL._SL1500_.jpg" alt="Build Book Cover" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;">, Marshall Goldsmith helps successful professionals identify the subtle behaviors that may limit their potential for further growth. The central idea is that the habits and skills that made you successful in the past may not serve you at the next level. Career advancement requires evolving your behavior, not just doubling down on what already worked. Goldsmith outlines 20 common interpersonal flaws that often hold high achievers back—things like winning too much, adding too much value (always improving others’ ideas), passing judgment, not listening, failing to give recognition, making excuses, refusing to express regret, and showing negativity. These are usually ego-driven and habitual, and while they may seem small, they slowly erode trust and relationships. One of the book’s most powerful messages is that behavioral change starts with feedback—and learning to receive that feedback without defensiveness. What struck me most was the insight that the need to “win” every interaction often causes more harm than good. Instead, Goldsmith encourages leaders to listen more, let others shine, and focus on long-term influence rather than short-term ego wins. Even highly accomplished leaders must stay humble, coachable, and open to change. Sustained success, the book argues, depends on continuous self-awareness and behavioral adaptation.</p>
<p><strong>Key lesson</strong>: To keep growing as a leader, you must let go of the habits that once made you successful but now limit your ability to build stronger relationships and influence others.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-next-level-by-scott-eblin" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-next-level-by-scott-eblin">The Next Level by Scott Eblin</h3>
<p>As a powerful follow-up to What Got You Here Won’t Get You There, Scott Eblin’s The Next Level: What Insiders Know About Executive Success <img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/718kckZw9TL._SL1500_.jpg" alt="the next level" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;">, dives deeper into the behavioral shifts required to thrive in senior leadership roles. While Goldsmith emphasizes letting go of ego-driven habits that sabotage influence, Eblin focuses on the deliberate transitions leaders must make when moving into executive positions. His core framework—**“let go of” old behaviors and “pick up” new ones—is a practical guide for evolving from a doer to a true enterprise leader. The book highlights the importance of thinking beyond your function, building strategic relationships, managing your energy and presence, and empowering others instead of trying to control every outcome. What makes The Next Level especially valuable is its balance of mindset and actionable tools: from reflection templates and decision filters to relationship maps and energy routines. Eblin reminds us that executive success isn’t just about what you know—it’s about how intentionally you lead, adapt, and grow. If Goldsmith helps you recognize the behaviors you need to stop, Eblin shows you what to start doing next.</p>
<p><strong>Key lesson</strong>: To succeed as an executive, you must intentionally shift from being a hands-on achiever to a strategic leader who empowers others, broadens perspective, manages presence, and continuously adapts to lead at scale.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-6-habits-of-growth-by-brendon-burchard" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-6-habits-of-growth-by-brendon-burchard">The 6 Habits of Growth by Brendon Burchard</h3>
<p>In The 6 Habits of Growth <img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/71HZJfJt6bL._SL1500_.jpg" alt="The 6 Habits of Growth" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;">, Brendon Burchard distills years of high-performance coaching into a simple but powerful framework for personal and professional growth. The book outlines six essential habits—clarity, energy, necessity, productivity, influence, and courage—that, when practiced consistently, help individuals operate at their highest potential. What resonated with me is how growth is framed not as a moment of inspiration, but as a daily discipline rooted in intentional behavior. Burchard challenges readers to ask better questions about who they want to be and how they want to show up in the world. The focus on energy and necessity stood out most: without vitality and purpose, even the best strategies falter. The book also emphasizes that real productivity is about focusing on what truly matters, not just staying busy. Influence and courage round out the model by reminding us that growth is tied to relationships and the willingness to act despite fear. It’s a holistic guide for anyone who wants to grow with intention and lead a more meaningful, purpose-driven life.</p>
<p>Key lesson: Personal and professional growth comes from consistently practicing six habits—clarity, energy, necessity, productivity, influence, and courage—that elevate how you think, feel, and lead every day.</p>
</section>
<section id="speak-so-your-audience-will-listen-by-robin-kermode" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="speak-so-your-audience-will-listen-by-robin-kermode">Speak So Your Audience Will Listen by Robin Kermode</h3>
<p>In Speak So Your Audience Will Listen <img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/61gWJ1L5VJL._SL1000_.jpg" alt="Speak So Your Audience Will Listen" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;">, Robin Kermode offers a practical and encouraging guide to mastering the art of public speaking and everyday communication. What sets this book apart is its emphasis on authenticity over performance—the idea that the most impactful speakers aren’t necessarily the loudest or most charismatic, but those who connect through clarity, empathy, and calm confidence. Kermode draws on his experience as an actor and coach to share tools that help readers speak with presence, handle nerves, structure messages clearly, and genuinely engage their audience. One of the key takeaways for me was the value of being conversational, not theatrical, and focusing on what the audience needs rather than what the speaker wants to say. Whether you’re giving a big presentation or just trying to speak up more effectively in meetings, this book delivers simple techniques that make a real difference. It’s not about becoming someone else—it’s about becoming more you, but on purpose.</p>
<p><strong>Key lesson</strong>: The most effective communication happens when you speak with clarity, presence, and empathy—making your message easy to follow and impossible to ignore.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-successful-people-think-by-john-c.-maxwell" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-successful-people-think-by-john-c.-maxwell">How Successful People Think by John C. Maxwell</h3>
<p>In How Successful People Think <img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/71G1mS5VnCL._SL1500_.jpg" alt="How Successful People Think" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;">, John C. Maxwell breaks down the core thinking patterns that distinguish high achievers from the rest. This compact, highly readable book outlines 11 types of thinking—including strategic thinking, big-picture thinking, creative thinking, reflective thinking, and shared thinking—and shows how each contributes to smarter decision-making and long-term success. What I appreciated most was how actionable the insights are. Maxwell doesn’t just tell you what successful people do; he helps you understand how they think and invites you to practice these habits in your daily life. One of the most practical insights was learning to shift between different modes of thinking depending on the situation—being visionary when needed, detailed when necessary, and collaborative when appropriate. It’s a reminder that success isn’t just about working harder—it’s about thinking better, more intentionally, and with greater self-awareness.</p>
<p><strong>Key lesson</strong>: Successful people cultivate a variety of thinking styles—strategic, creative, reflective, and more—to adapt, lead, and solve problems with greater clarity and effectiveness</p>
</section>
<section id="scaling-up-by-verne-harnish" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="scaling-up-by-verne-harnish">Scaling Up by Verne Harnish</h3>
<p><img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/71Dk9QB5sCL._SL1500_.jpg" alt="Scaling Up by Verne Harnish" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;"> In <em>Scaling Up: How a Few Companies Make It… and Why the Rest Don’t</em>, Verne Harnish provides a comprehensive roadmap for business leaders who want to grow their companies without losing control or clarity. What sets this book apart is its practical, step-by-step approach to scaling—focusing not just on growth for growth’s sake, but on building a strong, sustainable organization that can thrive through every stage of expansion. Drawing from decades of experience working with successful entrepreneurs, Harnish outlines actionable strategies across four key areas: People, Strategy, Execution, and Cash. He offers clear tools and frameworks—such as the Rockefeller Habits—to help leaders streamline decision-making, foster a high-performance culture, and maintain alignment as their business grows. The book is packed with real-world examples and proven techniques, making it an invaluable resource for executives, founders, and managers at any stage.</p>
<p>One of the most valuable takeaways is the emphasis on disciplined execution and consistent rhythms within the organization, ensuring that everyone remains focused and accountable. Whether you’re leading a startup or scaling an established company, Scaling Up delivers practical insights and systems that can help you grow with intention.</p>
<p>Key lesson: Successful scaling requires a clear strategy, disciplined execution, and a strong team—empowering your company to grow efficiently and adapt to new opportunities.</p>
</section>
<section id="your-strategy-needs-a-strategy-by-martin-reeves" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="your-strategy-needs-a-strategy-by-martin-reeves">Your Strategy Needs a Strategy by Martin Reeves</h3>
<p><img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/71yH6dBfQWL._SL1500_.jpg" alt="Your Strategy Needs a Strategy by Martin Reeves" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;"> In <em>Your Strategy Needs a Strategy</em>, Martin Reeves and his co-authors from the Boston Consulting Group challenge the one-size-fits-all approach to business strategy. The core insight is that <strong>different environments require different strategic approaches</strong>—and the real skill of leadership lies in choosing the right approach based on context. Rather than prescribing a single framework, the book introduces five strategic archetypes: <strong>Classical, Adaptive, Visionary, Shaping, and Renewal</strong>—each suited to different levels of predictability and malleability in a market. What I found especially powerful is the “Strategy Palette,” a visual tool that helps leaders diagnose their environment and match it to the right strategic mindset. For example, a classical strategy may work well in a stable industry, while an adaptive or visionary approach is more effective in fast-changing or disruptive environments. The authors reinforce their ideas with real-world business examples and practical guidance for shifting between strategies as conditions evolve.</p>
<p>This book helped me think more critically about strategic fit, reminding me that success isn’t just about having a strategy—it’s about having the right strategy for the time, market, and organization. It’s a must-read for anyone involved in strategic planning, transformation, or leadership in dynamic industries.</p>
<p><strong>Key lesson</strong>: There is no universal strategy—successful leaders must assess their business environment and choose the strategic approach that best fits its level of change, competition, and opportunity.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-product-roadmapping-relaunched-by-c.-todd-lombardo" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-product-roadmapping-relaunched-by-c.-todd-lombardo">The Product Roadmapping Relaunched by C. Todd Lombardo</h3>
<p><img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/71ZgEm3r38L._SL1200_.jpg" alt="Product Roadmapping Relaunched by C. Todd Lombardo" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;"> In <em>Product Roadmapping Relaunched</em>, C. Todd Lombardo and his co-authors offer a fresh, modern take on one of the most misunderstood tools in product management: the roadmap. Rather than treating a roadmap as a static list of features or deadlines, the book reframes it as a <strong>strategic communication tool</strong>—one that aligns stakeholders, reflects customer value, and adapts to change. What resonated with me most is the emphasis on <strong>flexibility, transparency, and outcome-driven planning</strong>, which is often missing in traditional roadmapping approaches. The authors walk through the full lifecycle of a roadmap—from vision alignment and stakeholder interviews to prioritization frameworks and visualization techniques. They provide practical advice on navigating the politics of product planning, managing uncertainty, and tailoring your roadmap for different audiences (executives, engineers, customers). Tools like now-next-later formats, opportunity solution trees, and lean roadmaps give teams a way to stay strategic while remaining adaptable.</p>
<p>This book shifted the way I think about product planning—not as a rigid commitment, but as an evolving narrative that connects customer needs, business goals, and team priorities in a coherent, collaborative format.</p>
<p><strong>Key lesson</strong>: A great roadmap is not a feature list—it’s a strategic narrative that aligns vision with action, adapts to change, and keeps teams focused on delivering real customer value.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-god-shaped-brain-by-timothy-r.-jennings" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-god-shaped-brain-by-timothy-r.-jennings">The God-Shaped Brain by Timothy R. Jennings</h3>
<p><img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/71B+USBDM2L._SL1200_.jpg" alt="The God-Shaped Brain by Timothy R. Jennings" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;"> <em>The God-Shaped Brain</em> by Dr.&nbsp;Timothy R. Jennings was a deeply thought-provoking addition to my reading journey—one that bridges <strong>neuroscience, spirituality, and emotional healing</strong>. The central premise is both simple and profound: <strong>our view of God shapes our brain, character, and overall mental health</strong>. Jennings explores how fear-based religious thinking can physically damage the brain, while love-based, grace-centered views of God promote healing, growth, and emotional resilience. Drawing from both clinical research and real-life examples, Jennings explains how the brain is wired to change—what neuroscience calls neuroplasticity—and how our beliefs can either reinforce fear or open us to transformation. One of the most powerful ideas in the book is that viewing God as punitive or authoritarian activates stress circuits in the brain, while seeing God as loving, just, and trustworthy leads to greater peace, empathy, and personal growth.</p>
<p>This book stood out not only for its scientific grounding but also for its compassionate tone. It encouraged me to reflect on my inner narratives and consider how spiritual beliefs influence emotional well-being and relationships. A truly unexpected but impactful read.</p>
<p><strong>Key lesson</strong>: What you believe about God not only shapes your theology—it physically shapes your brain, influencing your capacity for peace, compassion, and personal transformation.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-lean-product-playbook-by-dan-olsen" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-lean-product-playbook-by-dan-olsen">The Lean Product Playbook by Dan Olsen</h3>
<p><img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/81XiH0C5eUL._SL1500_.jpg" alt="The Lean Product Playbook by Dan Olsen" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;"> As a perfect follow-up to <em>Product Roadmapping Relaunched</em>, <em>The Lean Product Playbook</em> by Dan Olsen dives deeper into the <strong>how</strong> of building products customers actually want. Grounded in lean startup principles, Olsen lays out a clear, step-by-step framework for achieving <strong>product-market fit</strong>—the holy grail of modern product development. What makes this book stand out is its structured yet flexible approach, helping product managers move from fuzzy ideas to validated solutions through rapid iteration and real customer feedback. The book breaks the process into manageable phases: determining your target customer, identifying underserved needs, defining your value proposition, prioritizing features, and testing hypotheses through MVPs (Minimum Viable Products). Tools like the Lean Product Process, Problem Space vs.&nbsp;Solution Space mapping, and Olsen’s Product-Market Fit Pyramid offer practical guidance for navigating each stage with confidence.</p>
<p>What struck me most is how Olsen balances product intuition with data-driven rigor, encouraging teams to test early, learn fast, and build only what matters. It’s a highly actionable guide for anyone involved in product discovery, validation, or growth.</p>
<p><strong>Key lesson</strong>: Achieving product-market fit requires a repeatable process of customer discovery, value alignment, and rapid iteration—building smarter, not just faster.</p>
</section>
<section id="inspired-by-marty-cagan" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="inspired-by-marty-cagan">Inspired by Marty Cagan</h3>
<p><img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/61Nn6mDZ8YL._SL1200_.jpg" alt="Inspired by Marty Cagan" style="width: 25%; height: auto; float: left; margin-right: 10px;"> In <em>Inspired: How to Create Tech Products Customers Love</em>, <strong>Marty Cagan</strong> delivers what many consider the <strong>definitive guide to modern product management</strong>. Drawing on decades of experience at companies like eBay, AOL, and Netscape, Cagan breaks down what sets great tech products—and great product teams—apart from the rest. More than just theory, <em>Inspired</em> offers an inside look into how leading product companies like Amazon, Apple, and Google approach discovery, delivery, and team culture. Cagan emphasizes that successful products emerge from strong product teams empowered to solve real customer problems—not just deliver features on a roadmap. He outlines the roles of product managers, designers, engineers, and leaders, and how they should work together to validate ideas quickly, minimize risk, and ship with confidence. What I found most compelling is the book’s focus on empowered teams—those given clear problems to solve, rather than feature lists to implement.</p>
<p>If The Lean Product Playbook gives you the process, Inspired gives you the mindset. It’s an essential read for anyone involved in building, scaling, or leading product teams.</p>
<p><strong>Key lesson</strong>: Great products come from empowered teams solving real customer problems through continuous discovery, rapid validation, and a strong product culture.</p>
<p>.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2>
<p>My 2023 reading journey was a transformative experience, blending insights on leadership, communication, personal growth, and product development. Books like What Got You Here Won’t Get You There and The Next Level taught me to evolve as a leader, while Speak So Your Audience Will Listen and How Successful People Think sharpened my communication and thinking skills. Scaling Up and Your Strategy Needs a Strategy provided frameworks for strategic growth, and product-focused books like The Lean Product Playbook and Inspired deepened my understanding of customer-centric innovation. Finally, The God-Shaped Brain offered a unique perspective on the mind-body-spirit connection.</p>
<p>These books collectively emphasized the importance of intentionality, adaptability, and continuous learning. They’ve inspired me to refine my habits, align my actions with my goals, and approach challenges with a growth-oriented mindset. I invite you to explore these titles and reflect on how they might shape your own journey.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-faustine2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Faustine, Anthony. 2024. <span>“My 2023 Reading Journey: 11 Books That
Shaped My Growth.”</span> January 1, 2024. <a href="https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/01/">https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/01/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>book</category>
  <guid>https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/01/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://sambaiga.github.io/blog/2024/01/2024_reading_list.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
